<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The relation of all the last passages of the warres in the Palatinate, and how both armies haue disposed themselues vnto further enterprises Wherein is set forth the vallourous repulse of Monsieur Tilley from Heidelberg; with his great losse of men before it. Together with his iourney into the Marquis of Tourlachs country; and his plot for the taking in of all the three townes, Heidelbergh, Manheim, and Frankendale; with Generall Veres provision, to hinder that designe. Moreover the exployts of Count Mansfeild, and of Brunswicke in Alsatia; and of their passage thence through Lorraine towards Luxumborgh, and Burgundy; with the King of Bohemia's arrivall at Sedan. And lastly, the siege of Bergen ap [sic] Zoon by Spinola. Written from Frankendale the 20. and out of Lorraine the 23. of Iuly 1622. Stilo novo. Printed this eighteenth of Iuly.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08163</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.63</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120107</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99855307</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99855307</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20794</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08163)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20794)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1553:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The relation of all the last passages of the warres in the Palatinate, and how both armies haue disposed themselues vnto further enterprises Wherein is set forth the vallourous repulse of Monsieur Tilley from Heidelberg; with his great losse of men before it. Together with his iourney into the Marquis of Tourlachs country; and his plot for the taking in of all the three townes, Heidelbergh, Manheim, and Frankendale; with Generall Veres provision, to hinder that designe. Moreover the exployts of Count Mansfeild, and of Brunswicke in Alsatia; and of their passage thence through Lorraine towards Luxumborgh, and Burgundy; with the King of Bohemia's arrivall at Sedan. And lastly, the siege of Bergen ap [sic] Zoon by Spinola. Written from Frankendale the 20. and out of Lorraine the 23. of Iuly 1622. Stilo novo. Printed this eighteenth of Iuly.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.D[awson] for Nathaniel Newbery and William Sheffard, and are to be sold in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 19134.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 19134 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Mansfeld, Peter Ernst, --  Graf von, 1580-1626.</term>
               <term>Christian, --  Herzog von Braunschweig-Wolfenbüttel, 1599-1626.</term>
               <term>Tilly, Jean T'Serclaes, --  Comte de, 1559-1632.</term>
               <term>Spinola, Ambrogio, 1569-1630.</term>
               <term>Vere of Tilbury, Horace Vere, --  Baron, 1565-1635.</term>
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20794:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20794:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE RELATION OF ALL THE LAST PASSAGES OF THE WARRES in the PALATINATE, And how both Armies haue <hi>diſpoſed themſelues vnto further</hi> ENTERPRISES.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſet forth the vallourous Repulſe of Monſieur TILLEY from <hi>Heidelberg;</hi> with his great loſſe of men before it.</p>
            <p>Together with his Iourney into the Marquis of <hi>Tourlachs</hi> Country; and his plot for the taking in of all the three townes, <hi>Heidelbergh, Manheim,</hi> and <hi>Frankendale;</hi> with Generall <hi>Veres</hi> proviſion, to hinder that Deſigne.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreover</hi> The Exployts of Count <hi>Mansfeild,</hi> and of <hi>Brunſwicke</hi> in <hi>Alſatia;</hi> and of their Paſſage thence through <hi>Lorraine</hi> towards <hi>Luzembergh,</hi> and <hi>Burgundy;</hi> with the King of BOHEMIA'S Arrivall at <hi>Sedan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And laſtly,</hi> The Siege of <hi>Bergen ap Zoon</hi> by SPINOLA.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written from</hi> Frankendale <hi>the</hi> 20. <hi>and out of</hi> Lorraine <hi>the</hi> 23. <hi>of</hi> Iuly. 1622. Stilo novo. <hi>Printed this eighteenth of Iuly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Nathaniel Newbery</hi> and <hi>William Sheffard,</hi> and are to be ſold in Popes-head Alley. 1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20794:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:20794:2"/>
            <head>THE RELATION OF ALL THE LAST PASSAGES OF THE WARRES in the PALATINATE, <hi>And how both Armies haue</hi> diſpoſed themſelues vnto <hi>further Enterpriſes.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the happie counſell of <hi>Scipio,</hi> the Noble and vallorous <hi>Romane</hi> in the graue Senate, for the reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of his loſt coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, not to continue a Defenſiue Warre againſt <hi>Hanniball</hi> in <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> but rather to paſſe with the Armie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Carthage</hi> it ſelfe, the fountaine of their troubled Vexation, as that which would be a meanes, at leaſt to draw their enemy from the gates of <hi>Rome</hi> into <hi>Affrica,</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20794:3"/> their owne Cittie of <hi>Carthage;</hi> Now of this adviſe he couragiouſly vndertooke the performance himſelfe, at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the State of <hi>Rome;</hi> and performed it moſt ſucceſfully, to the ſafetie of his Country; and his owne perpetuall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</p>
            <p>If this pollicy of his hath oftentimes beene accounted worthy of imitation in the ſucceeding Ages; and alwayes to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue acclamation and prayſe; It is no ſtrange matter, nor need we to diſtruſt their courage, or their ſucceſſe, who at this day follow that courſe of proceeding in their Warres, and therefore howſoever I doubt nothing at all, but that after the ioyning of <hi>Brunſwicks</hi> Army with the Count <hi>Mansfeilds,</hi> they might haue oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Enemies in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> if it had not tended to the vtter devaſtation of that poore Country, which hath langui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed ſo long vnder the miſerable burthen of ſo great a Warre; yet for the preſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that remnant which is left, they haue now happily taken the way, to tranſport the warre, and conſequently, the miſery
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:20794:3"/> of it, into the Enemies owne Country, that they alſo may not be onely ſpectators of others calamities, but may at length taſte of the ſame Sauce they haue ſerved others withall, by a forced contribution at leaſt of ſuch money, munition, and meanes as for ſuch a populous Armie is requiſite; of which its very probable, they had ſome wants, by reaſon of the diſordered Diſaſtar, which befell the <hi>Brunſwickers</hi> in paſſing the River of <hi>Maine,</hi> where as its ſayd, much Baggage was loſt, and ſome men. Now, I ſay, for to furniſh themſelues againe with neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and to reinforce their Armie, by ſome new ſupplyes from the <hi>Switzers,</hi> and other friends; haue they taken their way into <hi>Alſatia,</hi> and ſo proceed, as this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Relation doth amply declare.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Frankendale,</hi> the 10. of Iuly, The Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> after that he had ranſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med divers Townes and places in <hi>Alſatia,</hi> where hee recovered a great Summe of Money, he layd ſiedge to a towne called <hi>Zanerice</hi> or <hi>Elſaszaberen,</hi> but it was ſo well provided that he prevailed not, but rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:20794:4"/> the ſiedge, and marched away to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Lorraine.</hi> Monſieur <hi>Tilly</hi> hearing of this, who lay before <hi>Heidelbergh,</hi> raiſed his ſiedge likewiſe, and ſo marched away in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Turlachs</hi> Countrey, with the moſt part of his Armie, having leaft onely 7. or 8, Thouſand at <hi>Wimpfen:</hi> and <hi>Don Gonzalo</hi> with the Spaniſh Forces at <hi>Landenbergh,</hi> which lyeth now over againſt <hi>Wormes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is ſayd heere, That they were ſo brauely entertained by Syr <hi>Gerard Harbert</hi> Governor of the Caſtle, and by the garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the Towne, that they loſt before <hi>Heidelbergh,</hi> aboue 1500. men.</p>
            <p>It is thought that <hi>Tilly</hi> wil make a bridg at <hi>Wimpfen,</hi> ſome 3. Leagues off <hi>Heidelbergh,</hi> over the <hi>Necker,</hi> hee hath one already be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low at <hi>Landenbergh:</hi> and that <hi>Don Gonzalo</hi> will make one over the Rhine aboue <hi>Wormes,</hi> and <hi>Tilly</hi> one aboue <hi>Spiers</hi> at <hi>Yden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heim,</hi> to blocke vp all the three Townes at once.</p>
            <p>My Lord Generall <hi>Vere,</hi> hath giuen or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Governour of <hi>Germerſheim,</hi> to take poſſeſſion of all the boates that hee poſſible can, and to burne them, that the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20794:4"/> Enemy be not ſerved with them, <hi>Turlach</hi> hath caſſeer'd his Armie, and is retyred to his Countrey, his Souldiers are vnder the commaund of the Barron of <hi>Helmſtat,</hi> and entertayned by Generall <hi>Vere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> hath ſent backe one Regiment of foote, vnder <hi>Waldmanſhanſen,</hi> and 600. horſe of <hi>Vbertrants</hi> band they are put in Garriſon at <hi>Mainheim</hi> and <hi>Frankendale.</hi> In the ſayd places, the Drum is dayly bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in his Maieſties name, to take vp ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Pont</hi> a <hi>Moſſen,</hi> in <hi>Lorraine,</hi> the 10. of Iuly, Count <hi>Mansfeild</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Brunſwicke,</hi> haue demaunded paſſage of the Duke of <hi>Lorraine,</hi> and obtayned it, ſo they are entered into <hi>Lorraine,</hi> and are now within 6. or 7. Leagues of this Towne, all the countrey flying with their goods, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Townes: Hee is ſtrong 24000. men, what hee will doe is vnknowne as yet: all <hi>Lorraine</hi> is in Armes likewiſe, All <hi>Burgundy,</hi> and all <hi>Luzembergh,</hi> take Alarum: The King of <hi>France</hi> hath ſent his Brother, with 2000. horſe to the Fronters to keepe them.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20794:5"/>
            <p>The King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> is in <hi>Selan,</hi> with his vncle.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Bruſſels,</hi> the 13. of Iuly, The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Bergen ap zoon,</hi> having received commandment from his Excellency, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> to attend him with 2000 men of his Garriſon, for accompliſhment of ſome ſervice in hand, was marching to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards him, but on the way had notice of the Enemies motion with great forces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes that Towne, to ſurpriſe it on the ſodaine in his abſence; whereupon ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing well on the buſineſſe, for hee ſtood in doubt, whether hee ſhould proceede foreward according to the commaund which he had received from the Prince, for by that meanes he might hazard the towne &amp; expoſe it to the Enemies hands, if the report of their intention that wayes were true, or whether hee ſhould retyre backe, for to ſafe guard the Towne: but ſo he might hinder the Execution of ſome exploit, which would be no leſſe prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to the State: but being confirmed in their reſolution who hold it better, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to ſaue that they haue in poſſeſſion, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:20794:5"/> to adventure it, vpon an vncertaine hope of gaining more to it; hee made backe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine with all poſſible ſpeede, and all lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle enough, for about an houre after his entrance, the Enemy ſhewed himſelfe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Towne, and ſo haue proceeded very furiouſly in the ſiedge, and haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived hitherto as valiant reſiſtance, but beeing already twentie thouſand ſtrong, they looke for ten thouſand more, with the Marquis <hi>Spinola,</hi> who arrived here the leventh of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uly</hi> at night, from <hi>Wezell,</hi> or <hi>Lyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berch,</hi> he is to depart againe to day to his men, who haue alreadie beſieged <hi>Bergen ap Zoon,</hi> and doe entrench themſelues; There are within twentie two Companies, that defend it brauely, and no doubt ſhall be releeved by the <hi>States.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
